<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Happy news to England sent from Oxford. 1. The joyfull hopes of a peace, and of an accomodation that is to be made between the King and his Parliament. 2. The Kings intentions to come to his high Court of Parliament. 3. The preparations that is made for his Majesties comming to White Hall, and the store of provisions of wine and other things that is laid in there for his entertainment. 4. The names of those lords that are nominated to goe to his Majesty with the answer to his late propositions, and to know who his Majesty will nominate and appoint for the accomodation and treaty, and the place where. 5. The security and hostage which is offered by foure noblemen, and also by their estates for the Kings security there and his safe returne to his court at Oxford, if in case the Parliament and his Majesty doth not agree. 6. His Majesties returning to London is suddainely expected, will under God make all those lying astronomers and deceivers, which prophesied of a great battaile prove false and counterfeit.</title>
            <author>Alsted, Johann Heinrich, 1588-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E89_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860091</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860091</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155727</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75275)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155727)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 15:E89[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Happy news to England sent from Oxford. 1. The joyfull hopes of a peace, and of an accomodation that is to be made between the King and his Parliament. 2. The Kings intentions to come to his high Court of Parliament. 3. The preparations that is made for his Majesties comming to White Hall, and the store of provisions of wine and other things that is laid in there for his entertainment. 4. The names of those lords that are nominated to goe to his Majesty with the answer to his late propositions, and to know who his Majesty will nominate and appoint for the accomodation and treaty, and the place where. 5. The security and hostage which is offered by foure noblemen, and also by their estates for the Kings security there and his safe returne to his court at Oxford, if in case the Parliament and his Majesty doth not agree. 6. His Majesties returning to London is suddainely expected, will under God make all those lying astronomers and deceivers, which prophesied of a great battaile prove false and counterfeit.</title>
                  <author>Alsted, Johann Heinrich, 1588-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1642 [i.e. 1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Johann Heinrich Alsted. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Lond: feb: 17:".</note>
                  <note>Woodcut illustration of horse and rider (representing Charles I?) verso of last leaf, filmed with with E.89[30] following.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155727:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HAPPY NEWS To England ſent from OXFORD.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The joyfull hopes of a Peace, and of an Accomodation that is to be made between the King and his Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Kings intentions to come to his high Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The preparations that is made for his Majeſties comming to White Hall, and the ſtore of proviſions of Wine and other things that is laid in there for his entertainment.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The names of thoſe Lords that are nominated to goe to his Majeſty with the Anſwer to his late Propoſitions, and to know who his Majeſty will nominate and appoint for the Accommodation and Treaty, and the place where.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The ſecurity and Hoſtage which is offered by foure Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and alſo by their Eſtates for the Kings ſecurity there and his ſafe returne to his Court at Oxford, if in caſe the Parliament and his Majeſty doth not agree.</p>
            <p n="6">6. His Majeſties returning to London is ſuddainely expected, will under God make all thoſe lying Aſtronomers and deceivers, which Propheſied of a great Battaile prove falſe and counterfeit.</p>
            <p>Printed 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:155727:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155727:2"/>
            <head>Happy Newes to Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land ſent from Oxford.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T this preſent, when in regard of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill warres begun and continued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, this Land was the vexed Theame of wretched miſery, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd by many pens, and all was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to become a Wilderneſſe of deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; Peace that divine Grace loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on us with eyes of compasſion pittyed our ſufferings, and hath lately brought about an unexpected change, and a long look'd for happy event of this bloudy civill warre. The King gracious in his owne diſpoſition, and alwaies heartily bleeding in the wounds of his Subjects (as himſelfe hath often profeſſed) hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies laboured by many Declarations for a peace with his Parliament, and now by the advice of grave and learned Counſell, his Royall Heart is enclined to embrace peace, by his Majeſty alwaies moſt mercifully defired; ſo that now we have ſtrong hopes that all diviſions ſhall bee be compoſed by a firme and ſetled Union, betweene the Kings Majeſty and his high Court of Parliament. This
<pb facs="tcp:155727:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>olution accompanied with many other mercifull pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, that his Subjects may know him in his owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall mildneſſe, and this the ſeverity of the ſword which he formerly uſed gave him as many wounds of griefe for his Subjects as it did blowes to others. Let therefore all true-hearted Subjects prepare to entertaine him with hearty affections, ſince London ſhall ſpeedily be bleſt with his happy preſence, to bring them both joy and comfort; thoſe that with prayers and teares have implor'd Heaven to ſee the King againe, ſhall now forth-with behold his Royall perſon, and with continuall prayers bleſſe the houre that brought him back againe to London: for his Majeſty is now fully reſolved to aſſure the Parliament that he is a patient and mercifull King, and that no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer paſſages ſhall dwell within his memory to ſeperate him from them, that he is ſlow to wrath, and had rather ſuffer than doe his meaneſt Subjects any injury, and that the ſad effects of War, as pillaging, plundering, ranſacking of Rich mens Houſes may bee all changed into a bleſſed peace. O therefore let our hearts embrace him who doth thus reach out his armes of mercy to receive all his good Subjects into favour. And that it may be more certainly knowne to all his Subjects that his Majeſty is purpos'd ſpeedily to come to London, and that the deſired peace ſhall with greater conveniency goe forward, and that it may more forward with greater ſpeed, being helped on by his preſence, proviſion is made for his comming unto White Hall, that once Sun of Majeſty may appeare in this Spheare from whence his beames darted comfortable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on all his Subjects. His Pallace now of White Hall ſhall enjoy his preſence. The Couet formerly turned into a Deſart, ſhall be now againe a Court. Majeſty ſhall now
<pb facs="tcp:155727:3"/>ſit againe enthron'd within the ancient walles of his anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Pallace, and with the ſame life and favour as formerly it did ſhall cheriſh the hearts of all his loy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll and moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Subjects, and the expected preſence of a King doth create a plenty whereſoever he comes; ſo it being moſt certainely know that the King will come to White Hall, there is preparation already made for his comming; the Genius of the houſe doth already rejoyce, and that mirth may flow in the breaſts of all the Court, there is great plenty of rich Wine laid into the Cellars, which doth hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily prognoſticate the Kings comming to his pallace of Weſtminſter, the inhabitants thereabout doe feele their affections warm'd, with a hope and expectation of getting by the Courts returne, and all London doth liſten to this newes as they would to a ſacred Oracle of propheticke happineſſe; and thoſe that doe not wiſh his Majeſties ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety and a happy peace, let them ſhip themſelves for new England, or for ſome other Iſland. The preſence of a King long abſent, and tranſported from them doth make all Subjects throw of all cares, all fearfull jelouſies, all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſts, and all narrow feares, and enlarge their minde to know nothing but joy, nor ſpeake nothing but <hi>VIves le Roy,</hi> God ſave the King. For now the King is comming to rejoyce his people, and that hee may confide in their perfect loyalty towards his Majeſty, and know that their Effence doth conſiſt in his ſafe and well being; foure No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, namely the Earles of Pembrooke, Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Holland and Salisbury, have for pledges of ſecurity offered themſelves and their eſtates for his Hoſtages, that the Kings Royall Perſon ſhall not onely be received into London with reverend adoration, but be as ſafe amongſt his true-hearted Subjects, as he conceives himſelfe to bee
<pb facs="tcp:155727:4"/>now amongſt ſwords; and if the happy agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his Majeſty and the Parliament ſhould by any croſſe fate be concluded, or that they ſhould not comply in that happy manner which is expected (and which God forbid) the aforeſaid Noble men have interpoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and given Hoſtages that the King ſhall then rule over all their deſignes, and take his Will to bee his guide in all his actions as his pleaſure leades him; knowing that he is a regular King, deſiring nothing but the liberty of his ſubjects, the maintaining the Proteſtant Religion, and the Priviledges of Parliament, and that all matters being brought to a happy period, hee ſhall if hee ſo deſire (if agreement be not made) be ſafely and royally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vay'd againe to his Court at Oxford. But if this City once againe enjoy his preſence, and that the King once againe refreſh with his preſence the drooping minds of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the day will ſhine glorious to the hopes of this kingdome, peace and plenty ſhall againe kiſſe each other, the Church much diſturbed by Sects and Schiſmes ſhall be confirmed in the true Proteſtant Religion, joy ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow the boſomes of the common people; the City ſhall flouriſh againe in Trading, the Country ſhall enjoy the plump fruits of Nature, the times long ſicke of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption ſhall grow ſtrong and luſty, Trading ſhall make the mechanick ſing, and ſuch a Jubile of joy ſhall ſucceed, that all the Land ſhall forget ſorrow, and with a cleare countenance relate the ſtories of our mixt diſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>We ſhall heare no more raging Drumms, no bragging Trumpets, but a peace as ſoft as the nights reſt ſhall cover the heads both of King and ſubjects. And what a happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe this is we may conceive by contraries; what pilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and plundering hath there been? Father againſt ſon,
<pb facs="tcp:155727:4"/>bathing their ſwords in one anothers bloud, as if cruelty were beſt expreſt where there ſhould bee moſt mercy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt. What would bee added to the fierce and bloudy battaile at Edge Hill? theſe and future events ſhall bee prevented by a happy Peace, by the Kings happy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and complying with Parliament, by that union and knot of love which is look'd to be tyed againe betweene them; and laſtly by the confirmation of a happy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Peace; for Heaven hath prevented all Petitions, and inſpired the Kings Majeſties mind with his Fathers Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eati Facifici,</hi> Bleſſed are the Peace-makers: Heaven is Wiſe and cannot be deceived, but hath brought about the great worke, to lay ſhame and ignominy on thoſe that ſcore out the doubtfull fortune of the yeare with falſe Predictions; and to confute thoſe lying Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers that will needes make the Starres guilty of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling of a great Battaile to be fought this yeare. God that rules the Stars will bring the King to London, Peace to the Land, and joy and comfort to the whole Common-wealth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
